<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: travel | Research in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-05T19:31:40+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arrival]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/19/arrival/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T23:53:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/19/arrival</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Dutch:</strong></p>

<p>Het was een aangename vlucht, met een van de  nieuwe toestellen in de ANA-vloot met de laatste technische snufjes. Er waren zelfs moderne Japanse toiletten aan boord.</p>

<p>Eenmaal aangekomen beginnen, uiteraard, de praktische zaken weer. Gelukkig zijn de meeste zaken geregeld door mijn gastheren, dus waren er tot nu toe alleen wat handtekeningen nodig. Het moeilijkste, inschrijven in de gemeente en het openen van een bankrekening, moet nog komen en zal ik, onder begeleiding, wel zelf moeten doen. Inkopen doen lukt al aardig met hand- en voetwerk maar ik zal toch wel blij zijn met de Japanse lessen waar ik binnenkort mee begin.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong></p>

<p>The flight was very comfortable, with one of the new planes in the ANA-fleet which had the latest in modern comforts, including modern Japanese toilets.</p>

<p>Once arrived practical matters recommence. Most paperwork has been arranged by my hosts so for now they only needed my signature. The most difficult bits, registering at the municipality and opening a bank account still have to be done. I am glad that I will be accompanied by one of my colleagues. Even shopping is still somewhat of an adventure, so I am looking forwards to my Japanese lessons.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In transit]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/in-transit/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T15:37:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/16/in-transit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The bags have been packed, the goodbyes have been said. In a day I will finally be saying <em>hello</em> instead of <em>goodbye</em>. For the moment I can enjoy the quiet. After arrival there will be some practical matters to arrange and I have already been asked to give a talk next Friday, not to mention this thing called research. This is a great way in which to welcome a researcher!</p>

<p>De koffers zijn gepakt en het afscheid genomen. Nog één dag en ik kan eindelijk weer eens <em>hallo</em> zeggen in plaats van <em>vaarwel</em>. Voor nu kan ik nog genieten van de rust. Na aankomst zal ik nog wat praktische zaken moeten regelen en er is mij al gevraagd volgende vrijdag een praatje te geven, om maar te zwijgen over onderzoek. <em>De</em> manier om een onderzoeker te ontvangen!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
