<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: aikido | in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/aikido/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-13T22:37:53+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small facts Sunday]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/11/30/misc17/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-30T19:03:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/11/30/misc17</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>English:</strong> Last weekend we had an autumn training camp at the aikido club, a few days of somewhat more intensive training sessions given by the teacher who is responsible for our dojo. A few students had an exam, the rest of could watch in seiza for a while. Curiously enough the next few days the trainings were a lot less busy than normal.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> せんしゅう秋合宿はかたひらキャンパスで先生のけいこだった。しんさをみたとき、あしがねむった。　45分ぐらいせいざにすわっていったから。</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-ft3SJSs/0/O/i-ft3SJSs.jpg"><img class="center" src="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-ft3SJSs/0/X2/i-ft3SJSs-X2.jpg"></a></p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> In Sendai even many Italian restaurants  serve the local speciality.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> ぎゅたんイタリアのりょうりじゃない、でもイタリアのレストランはこれをつくれています。</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-gc5dm2K/0/O/i-gc5dm2K.jpg"><img class="center" src="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-gc5dm2K/0/X2/i-gc5dm2K-X2.jpg"></a></p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> Here one enters the bus through the rear door and gets off in front.</p>

<p><strong>ひほんごで:</strong> 日本にうしろでバスをのる、ぜんぶでおりる。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small observations Sunday 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/01/12/miscellaneous7/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-12T18:58:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/01/12/miscellaneous7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> きょうひざがいたいです。きのうあいきどはたくさんすわりわざでした、そしてたたみがつめたいでしたから。</p>

<p>きんようびプレゼンテーションをしました。あたらしスライドをかきました。</p>

<p>あしたはせいじんのひです。</p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Koude mat + suwariwaza = zere knieën. Het wondermiddel dat hier in de matten gestopt wordt zodat seiza en suwariwaza een stuk makkelijker gaan is met de kou uitgewerkt.</p>

<p>Vrijdag heb ik de eerste presentatie van het jaar gegeven, dit was meteen een mooie gelegenheid om de opmaak van mijn slides eens te verfrissen.</p>

<p>Morgen is weer een feestdag: coming of age day.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> Cold tatami + suwariwaza = hurt knees. The magic pixie dust they put in the tatami here does not seem to work in cold weather.</p>

<p>Last Friday I gave the first talk of the year. A good opportunity to refresh the layout for my slides.</p>

<p>Tomorrow we have another holiday: coming of age day.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/slidetitlepage.jpg" title="" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small observations Sunday 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/12/22/miscellaneous5/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-22T19:28:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/12/22/miscellaneous5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Wiskundigen worden soms wel machines genoemd die dit:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1264b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>naar dit omzetten:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1265b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Kortom, koffie is redelijk belangrijk. Gelukkig hebben ze dat hier in Japan ook gewoon beschikbaar.</p>

<p>Ik heb net een aikido <em>training camp</em> achter de rug, een stage maar dan zonder gastleraar. Het het aantal kortere mensen licht hier wel een stuk hoger. Ik moet flink zakken en dat gaat toch goed voelbaar in de benen zitten.</p>

<p>Morgen is het een nationale feestdag: de verjaardag van de keizer.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> すうがくは：</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1264b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>から：</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1265b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>をつくるです。だからコーヒーがたいせつです。</p>

<p>このしゅうまつあいきどのふゆがっしゅくへいきました。つかれました！</p>

<p>あしたはてんのうたんじょうびです。</p>

<p><strong>English</strong> Sometimes mathematicians are called machines which turn this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1264b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>into this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1265b.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>So coffee is somewhat important. I am happy to report that coffee availability in Japan is good!</p>

<p>This weekend we had an aikido <em>training camp</em>, a stage, but without guest teacher. Japan does have a somewhat elevated ratio of shorter people from what I am used to, so during training I have to go down more. This is definitely noticeable in the leg muscles afterwards.</p>

<p>Tomorrow is a national holiday: the emperor&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the tatami]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/28/on-the-tatami/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T19:51:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/28/on-the-tatami</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> De training hier is iets formeler dan wat ik gewend was. Zo wordt er vaker gebogen, met een <em>onegaishimasu</em> bij het wisselen van de rollen. De senpai doet de oefening vier maal in stilte voor, benoemt de techniek, men buigt naar elkaar en begint de oefening. Een mooi staaltje van welgemanierdheid is het volgende.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Op de maandagen traint de aikido club op een locatie op de Kawauchi campus, waar we de mat delen met de judo club. Nu wil het toeval dat de aikido groep tussen de judo groep en de kamiza traint. We beginnen de les als gewoonlijk met de groet naar de kamiza en elkaar en de opwarming. De longen worden ook goed opgewarmd door het luidkeels tellen van het aantal keren dat een bepaalde beweging is herhaald. De oefening valt echter plots stil en we zitten tot mijn lichte verbazing met zijn allen seiza aan de kant. Het doel van deze exercitie is al snel duidelijk; de judo groep gaat beginnen en kan nu ongestoord de groet naar de kamiza brengen.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> Traininig at the new dojo is somewhat more formal than I am used to. Bowing when changing role is accompanied with an <em>onegaishimasu</em>.  A senpai silently demonstrates the technique four times, calls out the name, we bow to each other and start the exercise. The following is an interesting example of good manners.</p>

<p>On Mondays we train at a location on the Kawauchi campus, sharing the mat with the judo club. The aikido club trains between the judo group and the kamiza. Our training starts as usual with the greeting towards the kamiza and each other. During the warming up we loudly count the number of times a certain movement is performed. However, we suddenly fall silent and  almost instantly everyone is sitting seiza. The reason for this unexpected action becomes readily apparent; the judo training is about to commence and they also start with a greeting to the kamiza.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small observations sunday 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/24/miscellaneous4/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T11:28:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/24/miscellaneous4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong>
Uiteraard is het maken van fouten een vast onderdeel van het leven als buitenstaander, maar alsjeblieft mensen, als je op bezoek komt in Japan zorg ervoor dat je:</p>

<ul>
<li>niet voordringt <!-- more --></li>
<li>in de juiste rij blijft staan</li>
<li>minder luid praat</li>
<li>als je met zijn tweeën bent de naastliggende kassa niet bezet houdt</li>
<li>als je de taal niet kent jezelf excuseert daarvoor, tip: gebruik veel <em>sumimasen</em> of <em>gomenasai</em></li>
<li>niet voordringt, ook niet als je denkt dat dat voor iedereen sneller zou gaan</li>
<li>op zijn minst probeert te beginnen praten in het Japans, zelfs als je van te voren weet dat dit absoluut de mist in zal gaan</li>
</ul>


<p>Over de Japanse taal gesproken, ik stond donderdag eindelijk weer op de mat. Na een korte mailwisseling in het Japans (mijn collega had het eerste mailtje geschreven) was één van de actieve leden zo vriendelijk om mij door het doolhof van de Katahira campus naar de dojo te begeleiden. Ik heb een goed gevoel bij de mensen daar. Het ziet er naar uit dat ik voortaan bij de universiteitsclub van Tohoku University zal trainen.</p>

<p>Deze blog heeft een RSS feed, de link hiervoor zit onderaan de pagina.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong>
Making mistakes is a fact of life when you are an outsider. But please, if you visit Japan take care to:</p>

<ul>
<li>not jump the queue</li>
<li>stay in the right queue</li>
<li>talk less loudly</li>
<li>when there are two of you, do not occupy the next tiller</li>
<li>apologise for not knowing the language, tip: use <em>sumimasen</em> and <em>gomenasai</em>, see last week&rsquo;s post</li>
<li>not jump the queue, even if you think this would speed things up</li>
<li>at least start an attempt in Japanese when talking, even if you know beforehand this will not work</li>
</ul>


<p>Speaking about the Japanese language I was able to get back on the tatami last Thursday. Thanks to modern technology (for reading kanji) and my colleague writing the first email, my far-below-two-years-old-child-level Japanese was sufficient to meet one of the active members on Katahira campus. He was kind enough to guide me to the dojo. I like the feel of the people who practice there, very probably I will be training at the Tohoku University aikido club from now on.</p>

<p>This blog has an RSS feed, the link is at the bottom of the page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
