<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: research | in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/research/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-06-04T08:34:52+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[workshop]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2015/09/13/workshop/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-13T19:07:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2015/09/13/workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>えいごで:</strong> The past week I was in Tokyo for the CTFM2015 workshop. Again I got to meet old acquaintances and make new ones. The logic researchers in Japan form a lively community. Their enthusiasm has also been noticed by the international guests, many of whom are regular visitors now. The focus on a limited number of subjects has helped keep the number of interesting talks high. The relaxed atmosphere helped the younger researchers feel confident enough to approach the international guests. Many of the members of my research group helped with the practical things necessary for organising a successful workshop. I was really impressed by their hard work! The workshop was also a good opportunity to celebrate my host professor&rsquo;s 60th birthday, as he is the main instigator of the conference series.</p>

<p>During the workshop Japan had the misfortune of getting hit by typhoon Etau combined with a strong tropical storm near the east coast. Parts of Ibaraki, Miyagi and Tochigi prefectures were hit by floods and landslides caused by the heavy rain. Sendai city recommended 400000 people to evacuate due to the high water levels at the rivers.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2015/09/11/national/miyagi-warned-severe-downpours-sendai-urges-400000-evacuate/#.VfVOjZMvDPQ">http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2015/09/11/national/miyagi-warned-severe-downpours-sendai-urges-400000-evacuate/#.VfVOjZMvDPQ</a></p>

<p><strong>Japanese:</strong> せんしゅうCTFM2015のワークショップに東京へゆった。がいこくじんけんきゅいんたくさんきた。﻿プレゼンテーションはよかった。東京へきたゆうめいなけんきゅうしゃもそういった。おつかれさまでした！</p>

<p>まいばんともだちといっしょにごはんにいった。日本りょうりすごいとおもう。</p>

<p><a href="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-BZKm9V7/0/O/i-BZKm9V7.jpg"><img class="center" src="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-BZKm9V7/0/XL/i-BZKm9V7-XL.jpg"></a></p>

<p>せんしゅうもたいふうきった。東京にあめとかぜつよい、でもだいじょうぶ。いばらきけんととちぎけんとみやぎけんたいふうがたいへんだった。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pigeons]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/pigeons/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T20:01:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/pigeons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/pigeons.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Deze week weer enkel in het Engels.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> こんしゅはなしはにほんごですこしむずかしから。にほんごでありません。</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> The past few weeks there have been many mentions of the pigeon hole principle at work. First, for fun, I put it in my science dialogue slides. Then one of the Belgian guest mentioned it, after that it got mentioned several times in the workshop.</p>

<p>We start with the simple question on what happens if you put ten pigeons into 9 holes:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/pigeon10in9.jpg" title="image borrowed from wikipedia" ></p>

<p>In general, if you have more objects than holes, at least one of the holes will contain at least two of the objects. Exercise for the reader: how many pigeons do you need to guarantee (however you put them into the holes) that one of m holes contains at least n pigeons? Funny consequence: in Tokyo there are at least two people who have precisely the same number of hairs (even if you exclude the bald people).</p>

<p>The pigeon hole principle is also a stepping stone to another interesting principle: Ramsey&rsquo;s theorem.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Ramsey.jpg" title="image borrowed from wikipedia" ></p>

<p>If, for six dots, you connect each pair of dots with either a red or a blue line then at least three of the dots will be connected by lines of the same colour. The image above shows that five dots are not enough. The fact that you can do this for any number of dots (though the total number of dots needed is somewhat larger than 6) is known as Ramsey&rsquo;s theorem. Funny consequence: if you have a party of six persons then three of them will either all be friends or all not be friends.</p>

<p>By the way, for four dots all connected by the same colour you would need 18 dots, for five the number which is required is not known. I find it truly delightful that such a concretely stated question already turns out to be extremely hard to answer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[workshop]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/23/workshop/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-23T19:31:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/23/workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Afgelopen week was er de CTFM2014 workshop in Tokio. Een mooie gelegenheid om oude bekenden tegen te komen en nieuwe kennissen op te doen. De logica onderzoekers in Japan vormen een levendige gemeenschap. Het enthousiasme werkt dan ook zeer aanstekelijk op de internationale gasten. De focus op een een beperkt aantal onderwerpen heeft, denk ik, geholpen dat het aantal interessante presentaties hoog was. De ontspannen sfeer zorgde ervoor dat de jongere onderzoekers zich vrij genoeg voelden om te communiceren met internationale onderzoekers.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>English:</strong> The past week I was in Tokyo for the CTFM2014 workshop. This was a good opportunity to meet old acquaintances and make new ones. The logic researchers in Japan form a lively community. Their enthusiasm has also been noticed by the international guests, many of whom are regular visitors now. the focus on a limit number of subjects has helped keep the number of interesting talks high. The relaxed atmosphere helped the younger researchers feel confident enough to approach the international guests.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> こんしゅうとうきょうへworkshopにいきた。たくさんけんきゅういんあった。にほんのけんきゅうしゃはねっしんだから、このworkshopはがいこくじんけんきゅいんがきています。﻿プレゼンテーションはよかった。とうきょうへくるゆうめいなけんきゅうしゃもそうおもいました。おつかれさまでした！</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[science dialogue]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/15/science-dialogue/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-15T11:43:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/15/science-dialogue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1391.jpg" title="" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>English:</strong> The previous Friday I was invited to give a lecture at a high school in Yokote, Akita prefecture for the JSPS science dialogue programme. Yokote itself is a two and a half hour train ride from Sendai and was covered in a two meter snow layer. Luckily one of the restaurants serving the famous Yokote-yakisoba noodles was very near to the station.</p>

<p>Naturally when arriving at the school we started by exchanging business cards. My collection is slowly growing. The lecture itself was for a group of about 50 students. One of the hosts suggested that this was the longest period of time the students heard someone speak English. I do hope they understood the main message from the lecture: research in science is very exciting, especially when you do not know the answers.</p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Vorige vrijdag mocht ik een praatje geven in een school in Yokote, een stadje zo een twee en een half uur rijden hiervandaan. Bij aankomst werden we verwelkomd met en pak sneeuw van zo een meter of twee. Gelukkig was er een restaurantje in de buurt van het station die de beroemde Yokote-yakisoba serveerde.</p>

<p>Op de school begonnen we uiteraard met het uitwisselen van de visitekaartjes. Mijn begeleider had er zelf geen, maar de oplettende lezer weet inmiddels dat ik een klein voorraadje heb aangelegd. Het praatje was voor een groep van 50 leerlingen, eigenlijk iets te groot, bovendien zijn de leerlingen het Engels nog niet gewoon. Ik hoop in ieder geval dat ze het hoofdthema begrepen hebben: wetenschap is op zijn interessants als je de antwoorden niet weet.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> せんしゅのきんようびよこてへサイエンスダイアログのプレゼンテーションにけんきゅうしゃのひとといった。ついたときよこてやきそばたべた。よこてはゆきが２メートルあった。がっこうでがくせいに５０にんえいごでおしえた。ちょっとたくさんひとだった。メインメッセージはすうがくがおもしろい。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[history]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/history/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T12:51:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/02/09/history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is <strong>English</strong> only.</p>

<p>この はなしがえいごであります。</p>

<p>Deze post is enkel in het Engels.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/79/Hilbert.jpg">https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/79/Hilbert.jpg</a>" title="David Hilbert, source: wikipedia" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For a talk to high school students last Friday I was digging through some of my archives of interesting links.</p>

<p><a href="https://encrypted.google.com/url?q=http://math.sfsu.edu/smith/Documents/HilbertRadio/HilbertRadio.pdf&amp;sa=U&amp;ei=MvP1UsOkHY3jlAWCuoDQCw&amp;ved=0CBoQFjAA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHguRoGidUR5geSIRmqBlaKqJZeZQ">I found this document</a>, which contains a link to a <a href="http://math.sfsu.edu/smith/Documents/HilbertRadio/HilbertRadio.mp3">recording</a> of a radio broadcast of David Hilbert (mp3 file is in German, the document contains an English translation). The broadcast is an excerpt of a speech in 1930 in Königsberg. In the broadcast Hilbert talks about the motivations for researching mathematics and choosing the subjects of mathematical research. I believe this to be the oldest audio recording of any famous mathematician.</p>

<p>In 1900 Hilbert presented 10 of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert's_problems">23 problems</a> which would influence mathematics to this day. For my own field the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert's_second_problem">second problem</a> is of particular importance, as it gave rise to meta mathematics, proof theory and mathematical logic as disciplines. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Godel_incompleteness">Gödel&rsquo;s answer</a> to the second question, the incompleteness theorems, stands at the root of my own research of unprovable theorems.</p>

<p>I find it remarkable to be able to listen to a 1930&rsquo;s recording of my academic great-great-grandfather (advisor&rsquo;s advisor&rsquo;s advisor&rsquo;s advisor).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
