<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: miscellaneous | Research in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/miscellaneous/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-11T21:58:17+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small observations sunday]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/miscellaneous3/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T10:30:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/miscellaneous3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong>
Ik krijg eindelijk het gevoel dat er iets blijft hangen van de Japanse les: ik kon gisteren opeens, zeer sluw, de tekst おかわり¥50引き lezen. Met deze vergaarde kennis kon ik mijn tweede kopje koffie met 50 yen korting bijbestellen.</p>

<p>Een nuttige zin hier is  <em>&hellip; wa nihongo de nan deska</em>. (Wat is &hellip; in het Japans?)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Belangrijk om te weten: <em>sumimasen</em> (sorry), <em>dōmo arigatō</em> (dank je), of informeel, <em>dōmo</em>. Dat laatste wordt hier soms wel eens het meest nuttige woord in Japan genoemd.</p>

<p>Veel restaurants in het centrum hebben ronselaars ingehuurd om hun waren aan te prijzen. Ze staan op strategische plaatsen, soms op een paar blokken afstand van het restaurant zelf.</p>

<p>De warenhuizen hebben vaak op zondag mensen als hun mascotte verkleed voor de deur staan. Ik hoor dan wel verdacht vaak het woordje <em>kowai</em> van de kleinere medemens komen.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong>
Japanese lessons are paying off: I was able to cunningly read おかわり¥50引き in a coffee shop yesterday, thereby being able to get a second cup of coffee for 50 yen less.</p>

<p>A useful phrase to know is: <em>&hellip; wa nihongo de nan deska</em>. (What is &hellip; in Japanese?)</p>

<p>Very important to know: <em>sumimasen</em> (I&rsquo;m sorry), <em>dōmo arigatō</em> (thank you), or more informally, <em>dōmo</em>. Some people here assure me the latter word is the most important and useful one to know in Japan.</p>

<p>In the evening many restaurants have people outside advertising their food and drink. They stand not just in front of the restaurant in question, but also may be found at more strategic locations some blocks away.</p>

<p>The department stores sometimes, especially on Sundays, have people dressed up as the store&rsquo;s mascot standing in front. The adults find this great fun, but I do hear many a <em>kowai</em> from their children.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
