<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: laundry | Research in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/laundry/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-01T21:11:42+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laundry]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/laundry/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-30T20:17:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/laundry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>English</strong></p>

<p>Everyday actions get interesting if you do not know the language of a country. For example, losing the ticket for the bus increases embarrassment exponentially or one may have the irrational fear of accidentally pushing a button for the natto special at a noodle restaurant. Case in point:
<img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1175b.jpg" title="What?" >
The laundry machine at my apartment. Luckily with modern technology and Japanese colleagues using such a machine is only a matter of semi-random button presses. Which brings me to my main fear: I happen to like colourful shirts. Naturally I do not want to buy a detergent which may contain bleach. Some advice (<em>Iro ochi shinai</em>) and research later a solution is surprisingly simple: find a shop which has detergents with English words such as <em>color</em> on the package or, even better, a brand which one knows from the previous home.</p>

<p><strong>Nederlands</strong></p>

<p>De normaalste handelingen worden interessant als je er een vreemde taal doorroert. Wat te doen als je een buskaartje kwijt bent of als je de angst hebt om in een noedel restaurant per ongeluk knop in te drukken voor de natto van de dag? Ander voorbeeld:
<img class="center" src="/images/IMAG1175b.jpg" title="Wablief?" >
De wasmachine. Gelukkig heeft men tegenwoordig het grote archief met alle waarheden (internet) en Japanse collegae in de buurt, dus het bedienen van zo een apparaat is slechts een kwestie van een semi-willekeurige bewerking van de knoppen. Dat brengt ons bij het volgende probleem: welk wasmiddel? Ik had net een lading mooi gekleurde bloezen in huis gehaald, dus ik wil uiteraard geen Japanse versie van <em>wast witter dan wit</em>. Na het inwinnen van adviezen (<em>Iro ochi shinai</em>) blijkt er een verrassend eenvoudige oplossing te zijn: een wasmiddel met Engelse woorden als <em>color</em> op de verpakking of, nog veel beter, het merk wat ik al van het oude thuis kende.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
