<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Research in Japan]]></title>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-29T20:28:24+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Florian Pelupessy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[konbini]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/29/konbini/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-29T19:26:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/29/konbini</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> にほんのコンビにが４まんあります。コンビにがべんり。たべものとのみものある、そしてコンビにでコピすることとデリベリすることができます。よむひとがたくさんいます。インターネットでかうたかいものをげんきんではりにいきます。</p>

<p>いまももとみかんとチェリー ある。いただきます！</p>

<p>ももたろうよんだ。はなしはちょっとたいへんだった、でもたのし。</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> One of the many things making life in Japan easier are the more than 40000 convenience stores. Not only do these shops sell food (onigiri, bento, salad, fruit, drinks) they also provide, among other things,  copying service, photo printing, mail delivery and payment services. One can, for example, pay an intercontinental flight ticket at the counter using cash at midnight. Many of the locals also use the shops to pass some idle minutes reading the magazines.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago was the time to enjoy the cherry blossom season. Now is the time to enjoy the resulting cherries.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[little facts sunday]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/little-facts-sunday/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T19:40:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/little-facts-sunday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-5FNhwRM/0/O/i-5FNhwRM.jpg"><img class="center" src="http://www.smugmug.com/photos/i-5FNhwRM/0/X2/i-5FNhwRM-X2.jpg"></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>English:</strong>  There is a manga museum in Kyoto!</p>

<p>At the final stop in Tokyo the shinkansen (bullet trains) wait for twelve minutes before departing again, three minutes for the passengers to get out, seven minutes for cleaning, two minutes for the new passengers to board.  Often the teams of 22 cleaners per train have to wait for the disembarking passengers, leaving them less than five minutes to deliver a cleaned train.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> きょうとにまんがミュージアムがあります！</p>

<p>しかんせんはとうきょうへ１２分まちます。しんかんせんが7分まできれいになる！</p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Er is een manga museum in Kyoto!</p>

<p>Bij het eindpunt, in Tokyo, blijven de shinkansen twaalf  minuten wachten. Drie minuten om uit te stappen, zeven voor de schoonmaak en twee om in te stappen. Vaak zorgen de trage uitstappers ervoor dat de teams van 22 schoonmakers per trein deze in minder dan vijf minuten schoon achterlaten.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[coffee]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/coffee/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T21:41:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/06/02/coffee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/coffee.jpg" title="" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>English:</strong> Some Japanese people do take their coffee very seriously. There are lots of coffee shops in Tokyo serving excellent coffee.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> とうきょうはたくさんコーヒショっプがある。うまい！　あついあるときicedでいい。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/04/20/spring-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-20T19:26:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/04/20/spring-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/waiting.jpg" title="" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/waiting2.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> In sommige landen is het de gewoonte om, als de zon er weer is, goed aan te bakken. In Japan gaat men met de kersenbloesem onder de bloemetjes zitten. Mooie plekjes worden ruim van te voren gereserveerd, zoals hier in de tuinen van de Katahira-campus van de universiteit.</p>

<p><strong>English:</strong> In some countries people like to bake in the sunlight. The Japanese like to enjoy the cherry-blossom season. Places are reserved well in advance, as you can see here in the Katahira-campus gardens.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> がいこくはひとがサンシャインすき。にほんはさくらのときはなみするがすき。どようびのあさにまつひとのしゃしんをかたひらキャンパスでとった。</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/otokonoko.jpg" title="" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small observations Sunday 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/miscellaneous12/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T15:04:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://pelupessy.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/miscellaneous12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/bus.jpg" title="" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>English:</strong> This week the new fiscal hence academic year has started. Old faces are missing and new ones arrived. The university itself is getting busier again, with the new students filling the buses.</p>

<p>The new fiscal year also brought some increase in taxes. The shopkeepers are not abusing the opportunity to increase prices more and also blame this extra increase on the new tax rate, so now a cup of coffee at a certain famous franchise costs 302 yen. In many other countries this would be rounded to 305 or even 310.</p>

<p>I acquired a new Japanese camera. Naturally, I forgot all about these important dates and bought it after the tax increase. Expect lots of uninteresting pictures from now on.</p>

<p>Cherry blossom season apparently has started in Tokyo. As Sendai lies somewhat to the north it takes a few weeks before it arrives here.</p>

<p><strong>Nederlands:</strong> Deze week is het nieuwe fiscale en dus ook academische jaar begonnen. Oude bekenden zijn vertrokken en nieuwe gezichten bijgekomen. De universiteit is weer wat levendiger, met busladingen vol nieuwe studenten.</p>

<p>Met het nieuwe fiscale jaar is er ook een hogere BTW. Winkeleigenaren maken geen misbruik van de gelegenheid met afrondingen naar boven. Dus een kopje koffie bij een zekere beroemde keten kost 302 yen en niet, zoals in sommige andere landen zou gebeuren, 305 of zelfs 310 yen.</p>

<p>Bij het aanschaffen van een nieuwe Japanse camera was ik uiteraard vergeten dat deze belastingverhoging eraan zat te komen, dus de aankoop deed ik de dag na de verhoging. U kunt in ieder geval wat meer oninteressante plaatjes verwachten.</p>

<p>De kersenbloesem is, in Tokio, begonnen. Aangezien Sendai wat noordelijker licht duurt het een paar weken voordat we er hier van kunnen gaan genieten.</p>

<p><strong>にほんごで:</strong> こんしゅうあたらしいねんどははじめた。あたらしいひとがいる。だいがくはにぎやかだ。バスがいっぱい。</p>

<p>このねんどのほうがかいものがたかい。きょうねんコーヒーは３００円、いまは３０２円。ぞうぜいとき、がいこくで３１０円になるとおもいます。がいこくでみせのひとそがほしい。</p>

<p>にほんおカメラかった。ぞうぜいをわすれたから、このねんどにかった。これからしゃしんをたくさんとる。</p>

<p>とうきょうはさくらだ。せんだいはまだ。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
